[SPEAKER_02]: By not keeping the precepts rightly, you won't know what samādhi is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Samādhi comes as a result of correctly developed virtue, sīla, samādhi, pañña.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, does a person who is keeping the precepts, do they allow that pressure to arise?
[SPEAKER_02]: And by that, I don't mean go and seek out things.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You start polluted.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you start putting on, like, the brakes on your behavior and sense restraint and so on, the things will start coming up.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when those things come up, are you allowing them to manifest or are you immediately gripped by craving of getting rid of them?
[SPEAKER_02]: And doubling down in your behavior, doubling down in whatever observances you do, that's why you're not keeping precepts right, and that's why you're not discerning.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will not be discerning where samādhi actually is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly why that type of attitude of, I must get realist, naturally leads to that mixture samādhi that we often talk about, where you're just just focusing
[SPEAKER_02]: Mechanical...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the extension of already mechanically kept precepts and behavior.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, it's just the mechanical methods and routines, so that there is no room for your mind to sort of move and turn around and look at itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the whole idea of meditation is just borderline, like, you know, being asleep and switched off all the time, yet at the same time expecting some great revelation or pleasure to come from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And we said that before.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as you're meditating out of that craving of having not resolved the things that pressure you before your meditation, you are meditating with centrality.
[SPEAKER_02]: mismeditated, over premeditated, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: In that other sutta compares it to a jackal, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there's another sutta where the Buddha compares it to a stupid horse that just looks at, hey, hey, give me, hey, give me, give me the pleasure of reward.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he does not consider what the trainer will make him do that day.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's going to be whipped.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it going to result in this?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: All he sees is the pleasure of the food.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm just concentrating on, hey, nothing else exists.
[SPEAKER_02]: According to the modern standards, there will be a very successful meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the Buddha said clearly that that's a dumb, stupid horse.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not a thoroughbred.
[SPEAKER_02]: The host that actually is successful is the one that, sure, he has a tendency to the pleasure still, but he recognizes, wait, I will not focus on the reward, I will not narrow my perspective on just one point of satisfaction, I will think about where is the trainer, what is he up to, what is he going to make me do?
[SPEAKER_02]: If I look this way, he makes me do this.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I look that way, he makes me do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And start to discern these signs of, basically, mind development.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that all comes, see, the wisdom of that horse comes on account of already having taken the virtue and sense of strength rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when hindrances manifest, you attend to them rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't replace them with something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's already wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's already unraveling.
[SPEAKER_02]: All the wrong... most of the wrong views and notions and perceptions and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And certainly, it's revealing the nature of sensuality, the nature of the unpleasantness of ill-will, the peril of distraction and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: I actually think it would be, I think, very unlikely or pretty much impossible for somebody to take that virtue rightly in that way that you've just described, without, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Actively, or willingly, be willing to question your views.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, we have lots of instruction that you authentically think about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, definitely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the views naturally, and it's not accidental, support that type of wrong view of what's...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a public criteria for what is, what is, why you would, why you would act virtuously, or like some god or some kind of religion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an external idea of what is good and what is bad, but equally like the idea that if there's a bad thought or a bad mental state, I must get rid of it, whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And see, that's again like you... Would you be... Why would you be trying to get rid of something that doesn't belong to you and it wasn't your doing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, by taking it at face value, that I must get rid of this, you're taking the ownership of the mind that doesn't belong to you at face value.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also, you're not seeing your mind to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're focused on getting rid of the thoughts that are bothering you, you're failing to see that these thoughts are the result of the mental state underneath.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're too concerned to deal with them, you're not, you're not even gonna see that mind, let alone its signs and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_02]: We just keep hammering in through precepts and enduring things on the right level.
[SPEAKER_02]: You recognize, wait, these thoughts are a bait.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the mental state that they result from.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the state of mind, which endures like this, which has these characteristics.
[SPEAKER_02]: Simply by not acting out, you're already closer to see that wild animal for what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then it's like, okay, so, thoughts or not, this type or that type,
[SPEAKER_02]: They're the... they're the symptom, they're the indicators of the problem, of the mental state.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do I see that mental state enduring?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or am I just again falling back onto... oh, let me just deal with these thoughts, let me just indulge them or get rid of them?
[SPEAKER_02]: Either way, you fail to see the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And by not seeing the mind, how can you tame it, how can you train it, how can you develop it?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're still on the level of fully absorbing hay and reward of the food and taste and senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not succeeding in un-perverting it, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you don't act out of that pressure, yeah, that's again, like, whoever... whoever has been trapped, like, by bait or by an addiction,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because they couldn't give up that momentary satisfaction of following along the given action and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, let me just grab this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me just take it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll deal with consequences later.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the middle way again.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you realize.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yes, it has to... that pain that you're going to feel has to be there initially, just to the extent that you refrain from falling... jumping back into the trap or biting onto a bait.
[SPEAKER_02]: But with basic wisdom, with... well, not basic wisdom, with thorough reflection, frequently reflecting upon, yeah, okay, it's painful, but I do factually know that this is a bait, that this is a trap.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've seen it so many times.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, either way, I'll suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me at least now suffer in a different way that has potential for me completely losing desire towards any bait, any pleasure that would want to entice me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's how sīla develops samādhi that then develops pañña.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're not separate things you do, one after the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they're certainly, obviously, not mechanical things you do either.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they are mechanical, then they become separate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're doing them mechanically, you're not doing them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Abstract.
[SPEAKER_02]: Divorced from the actual experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you can, yeah, get into religious doctrine and, yeah, proliferate into academic.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's what that other, probably a number of other suttas say.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, somebody might be living withdrawn from sensuality, but they're not doing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're not developing their mind correctly on account of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, they're still, they're still adhering to that virtue, even celibacy and everything else externally, out of some, you know, faith or tradition or superstition or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, because, again, it's not allowed to enter onto that right level, because that's too unpleasant to bear, too close to home to bear.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always projected over there.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's that going to result in then?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you might not go... like, if you're out of determination, you might adhere to this, keeping these precepts for the rest of your life, you know, blindly, but doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that will then result into increasing of your views.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why it says, like, the Saṅghas and Brahmins, they do live withdrawn from sensuality, from these baits.
[SPEAKER_02]: They say no to them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you have the ones that go a bit too far, then ones that go... they don't go too far, but then they start
[SPEAKER_02]: Holding views, proliferating views.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always described on the level of, oh, the world is eternal, the world is not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those are like generic categories where every view will boil down to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Practically, obviously, you know, suttas don't speak in this
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, practically, what accumulation of the views on account of living withdrawal from sensuality will manifest is basically intensifying of day-to-day views and opinions and stances on everything mundane.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not about the universe is like this, you know, and how we get in a bitter argument on account of... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: But people would get in a bitter argument on account of...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't think monks should have their fingers crossed like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, what source you call for that?
[SPEAKER_02]: And people who start basically falling out, and then pulling rank, and introducing the whole hierarchical institution of, I tell everybody what to do, because I'm the most senior here, and you gotta obey to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like an army military command.
[SPEAKER_02]: Chain of command, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: And all of that is because, even these mundane little things, how you walk, how you put the cloth down, how do you cross your fingers,
[SPEAKER_02]: Become very intensified, and become very important for me, and I am moved, and I'm troubled by that that someone else does.
[SPEAKER_02]: Although it's in and of itself completely ridiculous, has nothing to do with it, mind will not let go of it, because you deprived it of the the main source of escape from the unpleasant feeling, which is pleasures.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then it's going to be finding pleasures in these other subtler things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as you either don't actually take up the virtue correctly, and for that, you will not have to go back to the start.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because that's just the opposite of composure again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in a way, this right type of enduring would also kind of reveal this what you refer as peripheral, rather than the... Well, it's already done on that level, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Peripheral is revealed by not
[SPEAKER_02]: Going towards it, or shunning it away, trying to get rid of it, to replace it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's already the wider picture.
[SPEAKER_02]: You haven't jumped into it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hey, wait!
[SPEAKER_02]: The trainer's there, watching me.
[SPEAKER_02]: He wants to see, am I seeking the central object to my nostril, watching meditation?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do I just expect pleasure to overwhelm me, or am I actually forsaking that direction?
[SPEAKER_02]: And am I just aware of him watching me?
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's my meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: We spoke about it before, actually.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you want to practice any degree of right mind, you have to unfocus from what you're being absorbed with, just in in colloquial terms.
[SPEAKER_02]: And this is even more so.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're trying to discern that mind that's kind of elusive and generally invisible to you, certainly in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're paired with it, you're identified with it, because you're not seeing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: By learning how to see it, you get to see it as an arising phenomenon that cannot be yours, even if you want it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's actually, like in that simile, you don't have to, you know, try and, you know, figure out how to discern the... where's the trainer and where's the...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite naturally by
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, refraining from being so focused on this hay or source of pleasure, that kind of naturally reveals itself on the right level.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to... And that's why, like it's said in other suttas, you know, like only once a monk has fully understood the danger in centrality, only then afterwards he can enter the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the danger, gratification, escape in regard to sense pleasures.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as you hope that, your hope is infected with centrality and your practice will be too.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, fully seeing the peril, the danger of the bait, of the track, of what's afront, not losing context in regard to it, learning how to be imperturbable and not move by it, then, that's your jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you can take that further in that direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not before.
[SPEAKER_02]: Before, that would be, okay, where's my hay now?
[SPEAKER_02]: I did work for a bit, but where's my hay now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Where's... where's the mouse I've been waiting for?